she's wondering about the responsibilities again
but being clear about what one is
responsible for so are you responsible
for for the well I'm saying that you're
not responsible for the arising of
possibilities for acting out of greed
lust or delusion see not so there's
always a release but there is a
possibility that you can act out a lust
but do you not responsible for that the
rising of that possibility
exactly that's that's in the level of
Mara they might have throws these
options at you hey hey but you choosing
to accept an act that's on you Mara
cannot make you do that that's why you
will never even well you're never gonna
see where the line for your
responsibilities is if by default you're
refusing to accept it even for the
obvious all these things Goodis us by
accepting the possibility that I can go
and have sexual intercourse hmm
therefore must yeah hey you know that's
just so then pressed so then the only
way for you to not do that is to ignore
the possibility is there if I must have
think about these possibilities because
I will be unable to restrain myself now
you have to do that in the beginning
perhaps until you sort of increase
mental strength
but you have to you have to recognize
that you must deal with it eventually
with the fact that these possibilities
will always remain wrong and they will
never the problem the problem was that
you could not help but act out of it oh
I just can't restrain from saying such
something when I get irritated well
actually you can the only reason you
can't is you can keep choosing to say it
but if you start recognizing it
it's not about not having an option to
say something we're not having an option
to do something it's about not being
able to resist that pressure of saying
something or doing something that's the
problem that's the problem yeah but if
you don't know well if you never look at
like say an option to say something out
of irritation you never stop and look at
it you're either just say it or try to
remove the option and thus I will remove
the pressure of having to say something
now that's overstepping now you're again
going in tomorrow's domain either
through overly accepting what he has to
offer you as an option or overly denying
in trying to tell him not to offer you
that as an option because you can't help
yourself oh please don't even tempt me
well that's not on you to decide
temptations are there because you keep
giving into them temptation our problem
because you keep getting into them we
keep choosing and keep choosing it so
now you recognize that temptations are
the problem but you can't stop choosing
them so now you try to prevent Mara from
tempting you which it means you react to
his temptations again no you made the
problem out of that which it isn't so
that's I mean if you accept that you if
your rule of thumb is to accept
responsibility for your choices even if
you're unclear about it you lean on -
well it's probably on me not because of
this so this you will stop blaming
circumstances including other people or
whatever else for your choices and you
will also stop blaming Mara for
presenting you with those choices or
presenting you with limited because
sometimes people complain in heaven
choices thus they are not responsible
for what they choose an account of
limited choices no choice is a choice as
such you're responsible for choosing it
doesn't matter whether the content of
that choice is great or limited
fortunate unfortunate doesn't matter
what matters is did you choose it
their circumstances are different for
different people that's how it works but
the fact is that regardless of the
circumstances whether the favorable
choice is agreeable choice is
disagreeable limited choices that I only
had offers of bad choices still the
responsibility for choosing is a new
here you not absorb the responsibility
doesn't matter how bad choices Maura I
have presented you with and that's the
nature of existence but for as long as
you feel justified in what you've chosen
because the choices were limited your
choices were bad
the choices were not as good as for
other people you're ignoring where
responsibilities and that's why you are
basically trapped by matter now because
choices were bad the choices were good
because you don't see where the line is
so you wonder as the window would say
into the hunter's trap not knowing that
that's a trap not knowing this is the
line if I cross I'll get trapped that's
the news and if I step out I try to stay
outside of it he can trap me I can go
around it but to the entry point it's
your choice you can do or endure you're
responsible for your choices regardless
of the circumstances and that's a hard
for many people it's a hard pill to
swallow because you know it's not like
easier it's not it's not consciously
done but it's kind of natural response
of an ignorant mind is to all I've
chosen that because of this so because
of that now because also you perceive
difference in people's choices
difference in people's circumstances and
as their own for me I had these options
I would not have chosen what I've chosen
I would have chosen better and so on and
that's probably true but it's beside the
point the point is doesn't matter what
options there are
doesn't matter what choices you made you
will be responsible for your choices and
that's that's there like that the
heavyweights of that lecture that you
make them choices that you make here
that's the heavy way to the recognition
of beings are owners of the kama kama
literally is a choice and an action that
comes out of the choice so your choice
is already in action so you realize
that's what the Buddha meant by like
really contemplate that because it's
only you knew and you will be bound with
the results it doesn't matter what
choices you had but say that's all pre
you acting on account of the choices but
once you do that's on you in other words
there is there's never an excuse to act
out the greed aversion delusion doesn't
matter what circumstances you were
presented with to act upon these were my
most pressing choices so to speak and
another thing is to like that's why you
cannot just step outside of that comma
that basically being being condemned to
choose you cannot step outside of it
simply by choosing this one account of
this because it's still about the choice
yeah you can choose better you can
choose worse choosing non-green on a
version on delusion is better then greed
averse delusion but in itself it still
keeps you bound to that pressure of
choice and that's the whole point of
like you cannot possibly not choose if
you say I will not choose any of this
you choose that and that might be the
right choice if all the other choices
are bad but still it's within the choice
that's right like you cannot in order to
step outside of basically free yourself
from karma and pressure of it and
samsara and everything all the
implications of your choices and the
results you need to become another hand
you need to fully approve the slightest
craving the slightest holding on to
things and so on in order to then truly
be free from the burden of choice but
you can do it by choosing the necessary
basis for developing that is to choose
non-green on aversion and delusion
regardless of the signal chances again
let's say it's never like oh well see I
didn't have the fortunate options to
choose so I had to choose greed aversion
delusion that's choice of greed aversion delusion
that's choice of greed aversion delusion
or choice of non very non aversion and
delusion is always internal regardless
of the circumstances but again if you
avoid this body fuel ignoring
responsibility of that internally you
will by default project the same
attitude external in other words
everything will be everyone else's fault
or the fault of the impersonal or far
only I've lived in a bad culture or if
only I live in a better state or in a
batch of society or better family it's
never on you because internally you are
unable to accept it as a result of it
you just keep mirroring the same
attitude elsewhere but it should be
actually quite a liberating insight yeah
you know after you after you deal with
the fries fries right of it right what
it's liberating yes but you need to be
basically courageous enough to accept
that weight anxiety of responsibility so
literally things are not in my control
options they're presented to you are not
in your control yet if I choose them
it's on me if I don't choose them it's
on me
if I abstain from choice well that's
another choice postponing the choices
but I choose everything is on me hence
the oh my goodness beings are on there
of directions like when people would
recognize that in the suitors
this is inescapable whether I go or stay
back or both or neither I am under it
how do I escape this and that's where
the Buddhist teaching come come into
play so as you're saying is it if it can
be initial fear like whoa but then I am
responsible means oh so you're not
subjected to chance and in here okay
rather your well-being is not dependent
on chance anymore because you recognize
well-being is basically on the level of
that like emotional background of your
choices and if you're responsible
choices then you will be responsible for
the result of those choices which is
that emotional bedlam so that's why the
Buddha would say the a man who's who is
not we sort of recognizes oh I should
act from my own welfare
of others he's the one who will not
neglect that because you realize that's
what welfare comes from I'm my well
being my welfare is by not choosing
things upon bleed aversion delusionary
sensitive prudent yeah so even if you
stick to it and if you don't develop
greater wisdom you're still gonna have
greater welfare internally then if you
just blind asleep blindly choose and
follow aimlessly towards whatever thrown
at you what they said on that and even
then by the way you have a criteria you
choose to be the criteria you can start
questioning as to why do I always choose
pleasure why they always resist choose
to resist pain there must be some reason
for that
oh it's natural yet but what is the
natural reason for it it's basically how
I feel so my the sole governing power of
my whole existence my values my actions
the results of it everything else have
to bear on account of it is simply my
feelings how I feel at a time could I
perhaps say no to how I feel yeah you
can't say no to the reason feeling or
you can say no to acting out of it
because that's another option see so you
don't need to act towards pleasure you
don't need to act away from pain but
that takes training that's why with the
brain of an ignorant mind and against
the grain of the minded about wisdom but
the result if you're going in that right
direction can only be can only rely to
the soul is a result of going in the
right direction a beneficial result yeah
and that's exactly what the literally
Kosala means means beneficial up to
Saleh's not beneficial yeah unbeneficial
unbeneficial yeah and couse Allah means
beneficial beneficial for you and by /
to oxidant for everybody else because if
your mind is free from greed aversion
delusion you cannot possibly be
perpetuating that towards others or
instigating it in others so it's a
win-win for everyone if everybody would
individually start accepting
responsibility not just for things they
do but things they can't
so for your own basically action by mind
speech and the body for your choices so
if you choose something it's not like
okay so I will not choose that's
impossible that's your choice so you
want to know the reason behind your
choices means basically that's how you
prevent obscuring your responsibility
behind your choices oh this is chosen
and I mean I chose this because he said
such and such stuff done this no no he
said such and such and I chose that to
be the reason for me acting like that so
how did I act then on account of me
choosing that to be the reason for my
action well I actively decreed I
actively the version there's no
justification for that now if you remove
greed aversion delusion as a motivation
for your action then you can say no he
said that and I acted like this without
greed without a version without delusion
so you're not blameworthy for acting in
this manner and not acting in that
manner certain things yes killing
stealing cheating lying that's always
blamed but other things are blamed body
if rooted in greed aversion delusion and
not blame word if they're not rooted in
those in those very things so there's no
like I must always act like this no I
must always not act out of greed
aversion delusion doesn't make it
particularly what am i famous hunter
here you oh I did not speak softly
enough doesn't matter I wasn't good was
it rooted in greed aversion delusion yes
then it matters but not because when you
spoken softly or not he's because he was
rooted in greed aversion delusion
irritation lust ignoring basically
indolence and so on so if you do that
long enough that training yeah not
acting out greed hatred delusion then
if you get used to that or during in in
terms of it you're incapable of acting
out greet agent alert delusion you still
have the option options always there
present by Mara yes but you're no longer
pressure before for a period of time
in other words Mara will keep presenting
you with options for as long as there is
a chance that you will choose them then
you will act out upon them but if you
have been steadfast long enough and that
there is no set time this this this is
how long it has to be it depends on
people but individually is determined
how long you need to be steadfast but if
you are steadfast long enough Mara will
stop heart of a leaving she will stop
even presenting entertaining jobs and
that's when the Buddha says in the
suitors after his enlightenment Mara
follow him for seven years trying to
find an opening like a crow trying to
get something to bite on and then he
gave up because he realized oh this is
this is that bastard is absolutely no
coming back towards that which I can you
know bait people with it so and then he
left it so let's I mean these and there
is this similar suitor who it says like
the Flies will be sort of flying around
where they can still perceive something
worth landing on but even when
everything is cleaned all the impurities
are gone
the Flies will still be around because
there's a habit of hanging around and
landing or something until long enough
there hasn't been anything awful for
them to land on and they leave they'll
find somebody else yes sir so let's say
the arrow hands
he can't kill anyone hmm but if there's
a there's a gun and there's someone some
criminal attacking someone else that
costs that option of taking a gun and
shooting a criminal for example just
well as a thought that suppose that
there that's a possibility in the world
but for him it's impossible to choose
that you can't it's impossible it can't
be pressured in any way to choose that
that's what I mean that there is
possibility but there are there are no
possibilities in the world independent
of individuals every possibilities on
the basis of individual experience so
talking abstractly about possibilities
in the world it's only applicable based
on the individual in other words you
can't talk absolutely about it so is the
person free from greed aversion delusion
motion of picking up the gun and
shooting somebody killing them is the
possibilities are saying the meaning of
those things have gone a necessary basis
for those things is removed so that's
where the Buddha would make those
declarations like our heart is incapable
of such thing is impossible to occur in
universe of all the eons and in realms
it's impossible for such-and-such to
occur for sotapanna it's impossible to
take anybody else as a teacher and it's
impossible and you if you still think
abstractly of these possibilities
independent of individuals you might
think who has that impossible to for him
to take somebody else teaching but if
you realize there is no such thing as
abstract possibilities independent of
individuals there is what it has to be a
basis ignorant so non ignorance a
version or non aversion last or non last
and person is a brutal death it's
impossible for anybody else for such
person to follow any different teach to
certain things require certain basis of
greed aversion ignorance to be acted
upon to be maintained once these things
are gone it's inconceivable for those
things to be done which means that when
those possibilities will cease for those
people so there is no possibility for an
ardent to commit murder or sexual
intercourse for that matter it's
impossible so the meaning of that object
and well that's the thing objects are
known through the mean
but usually yes people would kind of get
the meaning on account of the objects
but if you have fully understood the
nature of it you realize the meaning is
that which determines it and that's how
objects are known as objects so a gun
so yeah meaning like you might use a gun
to you know a murder nail something but
he better put a safety on he will not
have like he can't even have a memory if
he used to shoot people
for whatever reason like I'm good my he
didn't have a camera say he did yeah no
so here's a memory of using this to
commit murder but the significance the
context of it the meaning of killing
it's impossible thing to do them
that's what again it's all determined by
the intention there were those cases in
the suitors when a monk accidentally sat
on those like a big seed with many
cushions and there's a baby underneath
sleeping and he killed it I'm completely
unintentional and the way that made it
all you need to check it's lift up
things basically before you sit down so
that was his fault not killing his fault
was not checking so he was carelessly
just threw himself back from his seat
and he might have been another hand so
that's not killing killing is determined
by the intention to take away the life
yeah and that's that intention is
impossible for him because you cannot
have that intention without a degree of
perversion or lust or or or ignorance
which is completely rooted
so that's what is that kind of response
mundane sense of responsibility is the
place to start and never abandon it just
calculated more and more would you need
to get beyond that fear and into the
recognition net yeah this is actually
this is a great position yes because
once people start acclimating that
responsibility anxiety comes and then
you can sort of get like a choice
paralysis or two-speed flood whatever I
do but then you realize well that is
your choice now as well abstaining from
these choices because you can't bear the
weight of it yes well no you have to
actually accept it and in do it and do
the unpleasant a zone and recognize that
that's your choice as well but get the
results well if you persist you will
have to get it because in order to keep
ignoring responsibility that attitude
you need to keep maintaining it you need
to keep acting out of ignoring
responsibility you need to keep
maintaining the views that you are not
responsible it's someone else's fault
circumstances like for trends or when
people say oh you know maybe in the next
life and I'm not I don't have enough
part amis in this life how could you
possibly know that you just decided that
there's an excuse so you chose that to
be an excuse for abstaining from for
avoiding responsibility of your own
choices in other words you're
responsible for basically keeping
yourself in the state of non
responsibility which is greed aversion
delusion
and yeah you cannot possibly be
accepting cultivating sense
responsibility without a mindfulness
without composure without you know
carefully attending to what you're
choosing what you're thinking what
you're gonna say okay you have to
responsibility see if you're responsible
you're mindful you're mindful you'll be
aware of responsibility you know but you
have no excuses because an excuse you're
responsible for utterance is the only
being you call it
Teddy's excuse free completely his feet
he doesn't need any excuse he's
completely free from any blame and
excuses okay actually we recorded in the
blameless to play this one it's nothing
they're taking the basis for blame
doesn't mean people won't blame it cuz
ignorant people obviously perceive
things to be blamed which are not
blameworthy themselves but internally
speaking which is the only measure he is
blameless so there are it is excuse free he needs
so there are it is excuse free he needs
no excuses for every
it simplifies things in a way yes but if
like you know the simple context doesn't
mean it's easy means it's maybe you know
less sort of proliferated maybe it's
less defined less elaborated on which
kind of for some people might make it
even harder to transfer but either way
whichever way you arrive at it it's
gonna require work of going against the
grain of your existence of it
that's nature the track slide in
effortlessly if a track requires you
work to get in nobody will get trapped
same you know you want to catch a mouse
you put peanut butter in that humane
track you won't just go in it I mean
sometimes do they really really done
anything but even then so trap needs to
be effortless so what is the effortless
in this life acting out of sensuality is
effortless acting out of a version when
your language cephalus acting our window
lens the words you know let's thinking
too much too painful making that effort
of grinding against the grain it sister
I'll go winless resistance means I go
with the grain means that's why you're
playing wood that's why you're subject
to suffering that's why you're subject
to some Sun now because of the choices
or the lack of them making mind of
experience I didn't have many
opportunities you're alive
you're breathing your senses are intact
you're more opportunity than you need so
the only person would say
but even then people would say they're
responsible is the one you know born
blind deaf undeveloped incapable of
rational thought but even then they're
not born like that by chance okay
the Buddha says that you have to take
your faith there borned like that
because of the previous things are done
and you could see that yes in this life
you recognize that every choice you make
every intentions you act upon the
results have to be bound with you then you
have to be bound with you then you
realize day if I was born short ugly
sick or something it's probably the
choices I was making the past yeah I'm
no memory of it but based on the
principle that I can understand here and
now this is no different
yeah it's probably my fault
yeah well even if you don't necessarily
think it's my fault
doesn't matter what like what you were
born with what matters what you do with
it in that sense so even if you're like
you know not as good as others around
you it's irrelevant those things are not
the measure the measure is what should
you whether you keep perpetuating greed
aversion delusion oh you don't
perpetuate the diversion delusion so in
other words just by being born as a
human you're already more than fortunate
enough to deal with some sada
it's the best realm it's impossible to
deal with some sorrow if you're born as
an animal and it's virtually impossible
to deal with some sorry if you're born
as a devil higher because it's just too
Pleasant there's no no issues that you
see so human realm is the perfect
balance of pain and pleasure for you to
start reflecting on both which is a
necessary basis for uprooting the whole
samsara but you need to start taking
responsibility for what you think what
you choose because if you don't you're
blaming the pain or blaming the parent
pleasure for your craving towards pain
the towards pleasure or craving away
from thing that's in the nut tree not
your balls down today for as long as
there is a degree of avoiding
responsibility means your craving will
be justified by how you feel there is no
justification for craving so feeling is
not a new pleasure is not a new pain is
not the new neutral feeling is not a new
craving towards pleasure clearing away
from pain craving basically ignoring the
neutral isn't inflamed but yes there is
no linear connection between feeling
results in craving no ignorance is the
connection of feeling resulting in
craving you know you know it's a feeling
means craving
stopping out in the feeling you will be
incapable of craving mr. wires you crave
for pleasure some people would say that
because it's pleasant and that's what
you do yeah yeah but that's beautiful
right people say that people who
obviously haven't made the effort to
understand the nature pleasure or or at
least think about it
like okay so yeah I choose pleasure
because it's pleasant but what is the
reason for valuing the pleasure because
it's fun yeah
so what is the reason for me valuing
that which is pleasant a pleasure is
well so what pleasure is a reason in
itself means you will be completely
unaware of it you would just be blindly
you see a light you fly into it but no
you have choices you have choices even
on what pleasure you want so you are
involved so you can say oh it's just
because of pleasure because it pleasures
him automatically the reason for
pleasure you wouldn't require you're thinking
you wouldn't require you're thinking
choosing acting postponing to get more
why you do all of the why do you do all
of these reflections upon value of
pleasure if pleasure is a value in
itself if pleasure is a value in itself
experiencing pleasure is self-contained
fully why do you need more of it then
because you're not feeling more pleasure
by the way before you commit to
sensuality yet you're seeking more
pleasure on account of the pleasure
right here right now so there must be
some other reason involved between the
pleasure you have and pleasure you want
because if the pleasure you have is the
reason for pleasure you want you already
have it so you'll be craving free
sensuality free in feeling they will be
just a feeling but it isn't isn't it
so saying pleasure is the reason for
wanting pleasure it's incorrect you
choose pleasure to be the reason for
wanting more pleasure
so why do you choose that because you
value pleasure why do you buy your
pleasure because you're completely
ignorant of its perilous nature that's
why the website called the great danger
don't be negligent because it is truly
dangerous you don't know that but if you
take what the Buddha set of faith and
then actually start contemplating it you
get to see it and then you realize oh my
goodness I dodged a bullet here like the
relief off attainments like pay the debt
freed from the prison cross the desert
all the similes in Jonah's similar the
burden has been laid out the duty I
don't even I think I have free now